hey guys sh this side welcome to concept
and coding and today let's start with
our first authentication method that is
form login
authentication so uh in the previous
video we have already seen how we can
create a user dynamically and what is
the industry standard so this is the
very base of you can say that the
authentication method before we I know
that we eagerly wait that okay let's why
not directly jump to JWT which is very
very frequently used nowadays but to
understand JWT also we need to First
understand what was previously popular
what were the disadvantages how it was
working and then only while
understanding and learning JWT and O it
would give us a better sense okay what
advantage they are adding okay so let's
not skip this and let's understand this
like it would be a uh like very good
interesting uh you would get to know a
lot of things in 2015 I used to work a
lot in this but now yes uh it may be
very used limited purpose okay so let's
start without wasting any further time
so form login authentication it's a
stateful authentication method stateful
means your server is maintaining a state
of a client okay server maintains a user
authentication State AKA also Al known
as session so server maintains the
session so that user don't have to
provide username password every time
with each request so in this what we
have happened it you have a client or
let's say that user and you have a
server so first time only it provide
username and password at this point of
time Server create a session and stores
it okay now also send this session back
hey this is your session now for all the
subsequent request the
client do not provide username and
password it just provide the session it
just provide the session and server
validate the session if it is validate
the request has been processed
successfully if the session is not valid
whatever the session ID is provided by
the client if it is not valid or not
found the request is not entered
okay so that's what it means say so that
user do not have to provide username
password with each request for with each
request they provide a
session so user enters their credential
in an HTML login form this is for the
first time on successful authentication
a session is created to maintain the
user authentication State across
different requests okay so server is the
one who creates a session and and stores
it okay and also in the response it
sent now with subsequent request client
passes this session ID not username and
password very important it do not pass
username and uh do not pass username and
password it only passes the session ID
and server validates it with the session
ID which is stored internally okay so
I'll tell you we will see with an
example and also see this one why it is
important it it is a default
authentication method of springboard
security so if anybody asks you like uh
what is the default authentication
method is it jwd no still form based
authentication is the default
authentication method so if you have to
use a JWT we have to manually tell hey
use JWT otherwise if we don't tell the
springbot considered it as a form
authentication method I will tell you
where it is uh defined as like it is a
default also there are default URL of a
login and log out so login URL is/ login
SL logout so what is this like so the
first URL where we have to provide
username and password right so it has a
default URL is login okay and once your
session is created once your session is
created okay it is valid for a
particular amount of time we will see
that but let's say that you have to
invalidate the session before that time
you can call log out/ logout so these
are the default URL which are provided
by Spring boot for the form based login
you can use this when you use this login
you can provide username password your
session would be created and if you call
log out your session would get
invalidated okay we'll see that so this
is the default login URL log out
URL now one first thing comes to mind
that hey what is
session and when does it create it so
this is one basic uh flow i showing
you this is your client could be your
browser and this is your server the
first endpoint they hit is login SL
login which is also a default one okay
with this one they will
provide username
and
password okay
so when this happen what server will do
it will create a new HTTP session so
this is one object it creates a new
object this object is HTTP session
object okay it it contains various
information like what is the session
ID okay when the session was
created it's expiry
time okay Etc there are a lot more
information we will see that so it so it
creates a HTTP session and provide one
session ID and saves it in the subet
okay we can also save it in the DB also
but by default you can say that it's in
memory like uh it's in the subet itself
like Tom if you're using tomit it's
inside a you can say that tomit or you
can say in memory RAM so this object is
a stored
created and is stored in
subet also now
once the authentication happen username
password authentication happens sulet uh
session object is created the response
in the response in the return it set the
cookie also in the cookie the J session
ID it will put the ID this session
ID okay so it returns
that now your session is now on okay
currently it is active State now for any
further request from the client now they
are not passing you username password
okay they might be calling slash users
or slash anything okay they are just
passing in the cookie session ID and
what is the session ID is the one which
was received previously now once it get
server get it what it will do is it will
search for HTTP session object with the
ID this one if there is an active
session it will find it yes it fetches
it okay if it is f if the HTTP session
object is found and if it is valid it is
not expired it will fulfill the request
it will entertain the request whichever
it is
coming but if the HTTP session object is
not found or it is not valid already
expired it will redirect it to login
page it will red directed to the login
page okay so that it has to
reauthenticate
themsel so this is generally known as
when we say that session you this is
known as yeah a session has been created
means it is maintaining the user
authentication State yeah user is still
valid uh any request which comes in yeah
uh we can fulfill that
request okay so by default time to live
for the HTTP session is 30
minutes so this object which created
right HTTP session object by default it
is 30 minutes but depends upon sulet
right if it is a tomcat subet container
you are using then it is 30 minutes but
I would say that it depend upon the
subet container which one we are
using also we can configure it too if if
you don't want 30 minutes you want like
okay I want only 5 minutes we can change
that also we'll see
that and we can also store the HTTP
session in DB also so currently I told
you that by default it will store in
memory right but we can also make sure
that it can store in the DB because it
is possible that we have many server
server one server two okay if they are
restoring in memory the session and if
this is a
client this is your client if the client
request goes here yeah session object is
present in memory it would be able to
fulfill the request but what if the next
time client request goes to the server
two now server two don't have the
session okay then it will ask client to
reauthenticate hey first login okay so
it would be a bad user experience so
generally in that case in DB it has been
this session has been stored in DB
this session has to be stored in DB so
that no matter client request goes to
whichever server from there they can
query the DB F the session whether it's
valid or not and fulfill the request
based on
that okay so see this first in
application. properties I am setting
server dolet do session. timeout so this
is you can change this one I have
changed it to 1 minute okay by by
default is 13 minute and I change it to
1 minute now if there is no activity
from the user site for 1 minute then in
1 minute this session object will get
expired just see what I'm saying no
activity so only after 1 minute of
inactivity makes the session expired but
now let's say It's
121 okay now you are expecting that by
1202 my HTTP session will get expired if
there is no activity but let's say that
user made a request at somewhere in mid
okay so this expired time will
increase okay so it required a 1 minute
of inactivity total inactivity so this
would when when it was last used when
the last activity happened from there it
will again count okay inactivity of 1
minute then
only HTTP session will get expired so
that's what what I have written if user
activity keep on happening it will keep
on re authenticating and after 1 minute
session will not get expired internally
what it will do is when I say that it
will keep on re authentica mean
internally it will keep on increasing
the expiry
time
okay and second I told you that we can
store the s TP session in DB so it's a
very very simple way if you see that we
need this dependency which I told you
that u in the first architecture video
also I told you uh for the Spring
Security like we can have this session
spring session jdbc in the form.
XML and in application.
properties we can provide this three
configuration this configuration spring.
session. JBC do initialize hyph schema
equals to always means we are telling
spring boot that hey you create me the
table you create the session table for
me I don't want to create table myself
you go ahead and create a table so here
if you see spring boot will
automatically create a table for me
Spring undor session table for me okay
and I have told sulet do session.
timeout 5 minutes so after 5 minutes of
inactivity my HTTP session should get
expired okay and this will like um just
tell that we are going to store the in
the instead of in memory we are using
DB so here if you see that this is the
table which springboard will
create this is primary ID this is the
session ID which was
created what when this session created
last excess time maximum inactive
interval 300 expiry time so based on the
last excess time it will just keep on
ADD 300 and it will keep updating the
expiry time okay and this is principal
name is nothing but a
username so this expiry time will keep
on increasing if user keep on sending
requests based on the last exess
time okay so here if you see that my
session is now stored into the DB
instead of inmemory
so at this point of time I hope that at
least we are clear what is form login
authentication okay and when we are
saying it is a stateful authentication
means it is maintaining a session and
what is session
actually okay so since we are clear with
what is session now let's understand the
flow diagram of form based
authentication method very very
important and also by this point of time
you get to know that it involveed two
step first step is
login where user provid a username
password okay and through that we create
a
session second is request like accessing
the resource or you can say that request
or accessing the resource where whatever
the session comes it will add the
session and at this point of time it
will
validate the session
and fulfill the
request okay so now let's understand end
to end flow for this form based
authentication method and let's see that
if we have to implement it what is
required do we need to do anything so
first step currently there is no session
active user is loging for the first time
means session do not exist at this point
of time only user exist means and also
you already know that in the previous
video I've already told
that how to create user okay dynamically
also for in for testing the form based
authentication I have created a static
one but you know that how to create
Dynamic one uh but user has to be there
so assume that we have already present
user we have username password already
present user
exist now what the first step user are
trying to do is calling the API SL login
this is the default login page form
login page which provide okay we don't
have to code for this one spring boot
automatically provides right uh for the
form based authentication so when you
hit this API it will ask for what is the
username what is the password okay so we
already know that what is the username
and password we already have seen the
previous video I have given I have
created this is my user and this is the
password password and I clicked sign in
so here if you see that username goes
password goes and csrf token gos okay so
now what happened in the
back what happened when this submit has
happened so now call comes to one of the
security filter CH as soon as you click
sign in okay this username password
comes to this security filter chain now
see understand slowly what would
happen this is the chain security filter
chain and this is the first filter which
will get invoked username password
authentication
filter okay so now here the flows happen
so this is the first step which it will
do it will
create and pass the authentication
object to authentic ation manager so it
will create an authentication object
authentication object is nothing but
this object username password
authentication token it is nothing but a
child of authentication
class authentication class so it is just
a child of it so we are creating an
authentication object so it has your
principle which is nothing but a
username credential right it is
protected currently authenticated is
false it is not not yet authenticated
and no no other details present only
this much username password that's what
we are getting currently from
the
request now it passed to the
authentication manager and we know that
in the architecture video I've already
told you this authentication manager
delegate the request to one of the
provider so it will delegate it to Dow
authentication
provider okay now what it will do So
currently we have username and password
coming so this password if you see
currently it's not hashed form so it
first call password
encoder okay and encode or hash this
password whatever the incoming incoming
raw password is hashed
first okay so that is done after that
what it does it it will fet the user
details either from in memory or DB we
have already seen in the previous video
what's the logic behind it how it is
done okay so it fetch the user detail we
have a username right based on the
username it will fetch the user details
so user is already created so it will
get what is the username what is the
stored hashed password what are the
roles user has so all this information
it will get after that it will do it
will validate the incoming
username and uh password okay and this
password it has also done the hash okay
so it will validate the incoming
username and
password with the stored username and
password with this whatever the it was
stored in previously user already
created right so whatever the user is
already stored its username and password
and whatever the incoming username
password it matches
it if it matched then it will update the
the authentication object what all
things it will update it already has the
username it already has the password but
password it don't add it it just a
protected we don't put it now it change
if the matching happen then it says that
authentication is true yeah it is
authenticated also the role whatever the
role so during the user creation we
might have provided the roles which user
has we have already seen that so that Ro
also it will put this role is a for this
uh user it has these many roles okay so
it will update the authentication object
and it will return this Au uh fully
authenticated object return back to this
filter till now no session is created
okay only what happen is we have an
authentication object which has all this
information now which has roles
authenticated true username and yeah all
this information like account is not
expired it is enabled credentials is not
expired all this information is
present now what will happen now the
next filter it invoked is security
context holder
filter what it will do what it will do
is it will
first create a security context object
and put that authentication object
inside it okay so now you can say that
this security context has all this
information
actually okay so this security context
has all this information and then it
will pass this security context object
to http session security context
repository
class what it
does it will create a new HTTP session
object a new new HTTP session object is
created and it stored the security
context object inside the HTTP
session okay so this HTTP session has
all this information
now okay so you will get to know that
when this will be helpful why it does
that so first this authentication object
it stores into security context and this
security context it pass to this HTTP
session security
repository it creates a new HTTP session
object it could be uh like stored here
in the DB or in memory okay and this
currently it is empty and then later on
it whatever the security context is
there it saves in inside a HTTP session
object so HTTP session has uh all the
info you can say that uh like session ID
and you can say that all the expiry time
creation time and also it will hold all
the uh
security
context info like all this information
okay so I'll show you here if you
see okay I'm just starting a
server I'm just uh showing you I am just
doing
login so I have already created cre a
default username and password us e r and
password I have created P SS I have in
the application. properties itself I
have defined the default username and
password from the previous video you
already know that I have done sign in
okay user is sign in so means when I
have done this what would have
happened so means it has completed all
the flow so now let me check the
DB so spring set session so this is the
session data session ID creation time
last exess time maximum inactive expiry
time and this there is something called
Spring session attribute okay so if
I
see what is
the Spring Security
context and this is the serialized data
this is nothing but the security context
data this one
this all data is actually stored in the
session right so this is all part of
session data spring session
attributes okay so HTTP session object
is created and the
whole session uh security context object
is stored inside a HTTP session and it
is stored either in memory or
DB okay so till this point it is clear
what has exactly happened
now after successful
authentication if login endpoint was
used if login endpoint was used because
you know that after security filter
chain it goes request goes to dispatcher
subet from dispatcher subet if there is
Interceptor it will go there otherwise
goes to controller means some endpoint
has to be invoke right so if you are
using hash login endpoint so login is
just for uh spring boot form login
authentication if it is used then it
will hit the default endpoint like just
slash okay
so like this I
have first open this URL SL login I have
provided my username I have provided my
password I have clicked on sign in and
when I clicked on sign in the everything
happened okay uh how it
goes and fetches the user ex existing
user it compare whatever the username
password I have
provided then it uh whatever the
security uh context came authentication
object it put into security context then
it created a HTTP session object okay
and this security context also put into
HTTP session and since I am using DB so
all the details for the HTTP session
right session ID expiry create time and
also this uh this HTTP session has the
context right the security context
detail that is also stored there in the
DB and after that it has to call the
controller so it calls the default
endpoint this is nothing but a slash so
I have created one get mapping of this
default endpoint I just say hello so
that's why whenever click sign in it
will always print hello Okay so this
first flow is now completed
we know that how the first flow is
happened now the session is created and
we know that the session is created for
currently in our case like if we check
the DB I showed you right by default is
30 minutes but in DB for this one I have
showed
you it is for 300 like 5 minutes okay
because that's what I have provided into
application. properties 5
minutes okay now
yeah before that again like if you are
not using slash login if you are using
directly SL users so now what would
happen is it will try to look for that
okay you are trying to access a record
uh resource is it already authenticated
no so it will redirect me to a login
page where I provided a username
password the same thing happened in the
background HTTP session created properly
okay and all the session details either
in memory or DB and after that is done
it has to invoke the API so Now default
API is not invoked because I was trying
to access slash users so it
will call the same only SL users only
okay so default is only default endpoint
is only get invoked when you are first
trying to hit SL
login
okay now
the second point so we have completed
till this one your client and server the
client hits server with username
password server has created the
session HTTP session is created with ID
and it has all the session
details uh also plus security or you can
say that security context data which has
authentication authentication details so
it has has all this data either in DB or
in memory and it has return the uh this
ID session ID in response till that we
are done it is set into the
cookies now after authentication user is
invoking any subsequent apis let's say
I'm trying to hit slash users or slash
any other resource in the request I'm
just providing the cookie and this
session ID this session ID ID now what
would happen how it will validate it so
again the first part is filter chain
will come into the picture now what is
what are the filter chains the first
filter chain we get invoked is security
context holder
filter okay so now this is the so now
here if you
see username password authentication
filter is now not involved okay security
context holder filter will get involved
and and what it will do it will first
pass the request to http session
security context
repository it will try to F the HTTP
session based on the J session ID in the
request now any subsequent request in
the cookie they are passing the session
ID so it try to F the HTTP session
whether from inmemory or from DB it will
try to fetch it if HTTP session is not
valid or not found okay it will redirect
it to/
login but if it is found what it will do
is it will get the security context from
it you know that right in the HTTP
session object what we have put
above in the HTTP session
object we have stores the security
context and security context has uh
nothing but a
authentication of data so it fetches
the security context from the HTTP
session and Returns the security
context okay so what it will do is now
it will store the security context data
you can say that the authentication data
generally in one placeholder security
context holder okay so this security
context holder is available in the
complete life cycle of the request till
the point of you can say that uh your
controller get
invol this security context D holder
data is present so whatever the security
context is coming from the HTTP session
it has all the authentication data it
has all the authentication data
okay it will just put into the security
context one placeholder holder and that
is now available throughout the life
cycle of the
request so first thing done as soon as
the request come it Ables to it go and
find the HTTP session and it take out
the security context okay now it will
pass it to the next authorization filter
I will also tell you how authorization
works but in the authorization filter it
check does user has the permission to
access the resource or not let's say
that user is trying to hit slash users
API yes user is
authenticated from this J session ID I
am able to find the active HTTP session
and it is not yet expired I take out the
authentication data okay so that my
complete life cycle in the controller
let's say some flow needed some data
they can fetch it but I have the
authentication
data but authorization filter is also
required whether this user let's say
that this user
one has the permission to access the
slash users resource so that
authorization filter validate I will
show you how and once it is validated
yes it has the permission now the
control will goes to dispatcher solet
particular controller now it will access
the request follow the fulfill the
request so you got it like this two step
so if you just
see now you will say that okay now I
have to implement the form
login
authentication what I have to do so if
you just see we don't have to write a
single line of code everything is
handled by a framework
itself everything which I told you like
this filter chain everything uh like it
is fetching the HTTP session right
authorization filters everything is
already there in the
framework okay we don't have to do a
single line of code all we have to do is
configuration okay I'll will show you
and also I told you right it is the
default authentication method of a
spring board so if you open this class
this is a framework class spring boot
web security configuration if you see
that default security filter chain in
this one form login it has
set okay so there are different so it
has two default like it has used form
login and basic authentication it has
said both okay but form login it has set
it so we don't that's why we don't need
any code even it has set like okay even
if you don't tell anything by default it
will know that yes by default user might
be uh using form login only so all the
it the flow which I have told you
automatically it will go through that
flow
only so all I have added is the
dependency and the config so dependency
is that this is the security dependency
we already know that like till now and
this dependency is like I want to store
my session into the DB that's all and in
the application. properties from the
previous video you already know that I
have uh created a username and password
like hardcoded one I don't want to get a
random password every
time okay so from in the previous video
I've already showed you what are the
different ways to create a username
password okay and this is the hardcoded
one is just for the testing purpose it's
not recommended in the live and the live
recommendation I've already shown in the
previous video so I have created a
username password so when the user uh
when during the server application
startup time one user would be created
with this user and with this
password okay and this is the second
thing which I have told like I want to
store the session into the
DB and I want spring boot to create the
tables for me and the session time out I
want 5
minutes
okay so we can test this one like if you
hit the API SL login API you will
provide username and the password P SS
okay now if you click on the sign in
okay so you will see that in the
response after the successful
authentication like uh in the response
set cookie you will get a session a
session has been sent to
you okay and later on any API you will
is okay you will see that in the
request we are passing that session ID
again okay so this is in the request we
are passing it to the
server so we have done nothing all we
have added is form and application.
properties and this all has been handled
we are able to do all of this
stuff okay
now one thing comes to your mind that
okay sh let's say that if I want to
change few things like I don't want this
default login page or default logout
page I want to create mine mine login
page M log out page or I want to relax
authentication on few endpoints if you
see by default in the framework what it
says that no matter any request you have
to be
authenticated but let's say that you
have like hey sh I have certain public
API
I have some public apis for which
authentication is not required I don't
want to force the user to authenticate
these are public API how can I relax
them simple write your own security
filter chain very simple right so in my
configuration at theate configuration I
have created my own
configuration so here if you see that I
have said the same thing
any request
authenticated but any request matches
this any API let's say/ users API permit
all no need to authenticate it so I am
considering this is my public API this
is just for example right so let's say
that/ user is your public API you don't
want any authentication so I just put do
permit all and find any other request
authenticate and here if you see I have
just used form login
with
defaults so customized what with default
so here with default itself login page
is your default SL logout is your
default so if you want your custom login
page you can change here like dot form
login you can change something like form
so something form. login what is your
login page something my hyen login
something like this you can change it
whatever you want to do but what I mean
to say that you have to write your own
security filter
chain right so now you get to know at
this point of time let's say that if you
have to work with JWT you will always
see that we have to write this security
filter change because we don't have to
use form login we have to tell something
like hey something JWT something because
form login is the default one otherwise
we have to tell it so now you know that
okay why for in my company we are using
form but we are not writing this Bean
why because it's already the by default
one okay now form based authentication
is clear right but still one thing left
is authorization
filter and also one more thing I am not
going into like we have seen that right
by default uh the spring creates the
table for you that uh session session
tables
uh this session tables right where it
gone yeah spring underscore session and
also there is one more table right
spring undor session attribute something
so these two tables it creates where it
has all the data
present we can also do that we can
instead of relying on Spring to create
table for us we can override and we can
create our own
table I don't want to go into that way
because uh this is I don't think that it
is widely used now but this is to set a
fundamental in
20156 when I was working we were writing
our own tables and we were managing
those table like we have more tables and
we are managing the session whether to
increase the time or not okay whether to
uh update this column or not like all
this
stuff but I don't want to go in that way
like where we are managing by ourselves
just consider that it is possible
otherwise if you don't require it you
have the basic need let the spring
manage your tables spring tables for you
and you already know that why it is
required because you have different
servers then you need to store somewhere
otherwise request goes to different
server if it is stickiness is not
maintained then there you will ask
unnecessary user to
authenticate
okay yeah now let's come back again to
authorization filter which is
left so as I already told you that once
the user is
authenticated when user is trying to
access any
resource authorization check is
mandatory it is done to make sure that
user has the permission to access it we
already seen that by
default spring boot security do not put
any
restriction again do not put any
restriction on any resource we have to
do it
manually now let's say that you have
endpoint
sluser
users by default if user is
authenticated if user one try to access
it authenticated it will access it user
two authenticate and it try to access it
it will let it exit it don't put any
restriction by default we have to do it
manually that oh hey for user one look
for this role whether this should be
user role for user uh to look for this
role admin role it should have while
accessing this resource so we have to
tell that if you don't tell that no
restriction if you are authenticated go
and access the
resource so authorization has two
phases phase one so phase one is like
you know that we have security chain
filters security chain
okay after that security chain filter
chain what is that your dispatcher sulet
and then there is your controller
ultimately okay so authorization done at
two places first at
filter filter level second at controller
level authorization check as part of
security
filter that's where our authorization
filters comes into the picture right
and the second phase is authorization
check after request passes the security
filter but reaches the controller so
request passes the security filter but
reach till the controller now there I'm
checking that user is has the authority
to access the resource or not so we will
see this later because currently we
are looking at the
filter okay so this one how to do at the
controller level authorization we will
see later because that is common for
form based basic JWT or any other
authentication method because the
control now re still controller now
there we have to do an authorization so
that part is common for all the
authentication
method but this part security filter
this is uh unique for each one so for
form base we know that authorization
filter comes into the picture we have
already seen that so how it does
that so if you look that it's very
simple I told you that by default spring
boot security do not restrict any
resource we have to do it manually so
I'm doing it manually in the security
filter
chain I am telling any request matches
this/
users should have the role has Ro
user this is just a string you can give
anything okay and and internally it
append r l roore so it append this so
ultimately internally it would become
role
user like you can give anything it's a
string but maintain uh like follow some
uh proper naming
conventions okay so what I'm telling is
any request matchers like/ users should
have the role
user okay so it it will authenticate
also it's not like it will not
authenticate authenticate plus has role
also will be
checked also here in the application.
property I have added while creation of
a user and password I have also assigned
this user or role user okay we have
already seen that like in the dynamic
also how we can while creating a user
how we can assign a role so while the
application is start up user is created
let's say there is some user table user
is created with usern name password and
the role user is
created okay and we have mentioned that/
user has the role user it required this
now what would
happen now I am manually restricting
that any user trying to access this
endpoint should have this
role okay and also I told you no need to
add Ro underscore it will automatically
get
added now in
not authentication filter it is
authorization
filter now in authorization filter it
will
validate okay before I say anything just
a very quick recap when the
authorization filter is invoked what is
passed to it security context holder
what security context holder holds
security context holder hold security
context data which has all authenticated
data authentication data is nothing but
this this this is authenticated data
right so it has all the user role
everything which is there in the DB only
from DB it found right it call it
fetches the user detail from the DB
username password role it has all this
data all right
so now when authorization filter invoke
it will validate okay
user is trying to access this user's
endpoint and this endpoint required role
user roore user this because we have
tell
here and it knows that authorization
filter got security context this has
authentication data where all the user
details is present all the username
password role is present so it knows
that this user has what Ro Ro so we have
already given this
role okay so it will match if it match
well and good it will let it go through
the controller if not it will pass
forbidden
exception forbidden this one and in
application. properties let's say I am
giving that this user has admin
role but not uh but this API required
this user role now now let's start the
server let's first user try
to let's first try to user
login user
pass user is successfully login now I'm
trying to log in user AP endpoint when I
hit it says that forbidden 403
there is a mismatch in
the role and authorization filter is the
one which throws the Forbidden
exception also we can give as many role
to uh user like more than one okay so
here if you
see request matchers this API if anybody
has now I'm using has any role now I can
provide like a list user add
anything and
similarly I have provided here like this
by comma separated I can provide as many
roles I
required
okay so I hope by this point of time
form login authentication is clear so
there are few questions can come
sometimes during discussion how to
control the session per user now let's
say that I have one user user
one it it is using browser one and it
has created session here now the same
user using browser 2 or another window
created another session in cognito mode
or another session two same user session
three what
if it create thousand of session so we
have to control the sessions right per
user so we can also control it very
simple way there is something called
session management
in the session management for session we
can set the maximum session is one and
after that Max sessions prevent login
true so with this two Fields
set like one one time you are able to do
create a session works fine second time
when you are trying to do it will say
that maximum session of one user for
this principal
exceeded okay so it will try to like
with the username it will try to fch
okay because with username only it
fetches the data from the DB so only one
user per session is allowed after that
if it exceed it will throw an exception
if you want multiple session for you can
just increase this 2 3 4 something like
that they also sometime asked this what
is session creation policy we haven't
discussed anything like that right but
if you see the
that do session management do session
creation policy is Riff required even if
we don't write this this is by default
added if required so what is this
session creation policies so there are
four values it can take if required
always never
stateless if required means HTTP session
is only created when needed and this is
the default that's why above we haven't
used
it what it mean if only required so
let's say that I have a public API I
have a public API okay for that one HTTP
session will not be
created okay so it only created for
which it is required wherever
authentication is required it create HTP
session for that only but if you change
it and use always
always then no matter what HTTP session
is always
created if already HTTP session is
present then it will reuse it but no
matter whether it's a public API or not
a public
API STP session would get
created okay but generally for public
apis authentication is not required so
generally you don't require you don't
need to maintain the state because let's
say public API is hit by uh millions of
time you don't have to maintain an
authentication it's just like
informational okay so that's why if
required is generally preferred and it
default you don't need to create a
session for each apis also for whichever
it is not required never says that do
not create a session always use if
present okay and Stat less is like no
session is created at all all it is used
for stateless application like
JWT okay so this is what session
creation policy
mean and this is how generally we
set and the last question which can come
in like what are the disadvantage of
form based authentication I think by
this point of time you already got it
like first is like as we have discussed
in the previous vulnerable to security
issues like csrf we have already
discussed very beginning all the attacks
with demo okay how the csrf demo session
hijacking is possible so form based
authentication is vulnerable to it but
if you see that by default csrf is
enabled for form based login you can
disable it also in the security filter
change you can say that csrf disabled
but we should not do this for form based
authentication always unable it csrf
right because it is vulnerable to attack
like csrf
so do not disable it this is just for
sample I'm showing you you can disable
it and session hijacking so you know
that the session ID is passed in the
cookie so it is uh very much likely that
your session get hijacked it got is
stolen and using this your J session
ID the attacker uses it your resources
access your
resources the second is the session
management is a big overhead So
currently everything we have seen is
handled to
framework but I told you that when in
2015 and 16 we were working in a company
it was handled all manually like because
as per the business lot of things in the
session we have to uh manage according
to business need right so generally if
it is a very simple business then yeah
you can use framework but definitely as
the business grows lot of custom needs
required so you have to manage the
session yourself so session management
is a big overhead you have to have like
session tables you have to manage its
expiry and all this stuff right and also
now in case of distributed system like
it would be like a SC scalability issue
for
sure and this is the subsequent issue is
that database load now you have in the
distributed system let's say you have
multiple services or let's say that even
for one service you have
multiple
instances definitely you need a DB then
like you can't have uh
session stored in memory what if as I
told because nowadays we have load
balancer in front of the client it can
pass the request to anybody so if
earlier session is created here user
says that you are authenticated now the
second time it try to
access the control goes to the second
instance now you say that hey where is
the the session or and it will say that
hey reauthenticate SL login page again
so this is a bad user experience okay so
that's why in memory is not used if you
have multiple instances you have to put
into DB so that all the instances F the
session from the DB so there are
multiple servers then we need to store
in the session into DB or Cache so again
memory you required lookup time is
required which increases the
latency
okay I hope this form login
authentication is totally clear right do
practice it with your hand even though
it is not very frequently used nowadays
JWT is very popular but this is the
fundamental if our this flow is clear
right all other authentication method we
will get to know that how they are
working why exactly we need those okay
and if there is any question feel free
to Ping in the comment section we'll
discuss more see you soon bye